{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The attainment of individual and organisational goals is mutually interdependent and linked by a common denominator - employee work motivation. Organisational members are motivated to satisfy their personal goals, and they contribute their efforts to the attainment of organisational objectives as means of achieving these personal goals. The passage best supports the statement that motivation -", "opta": "encourages an individual to give priority to personal goals over organisational goals.", "optb": "is crucial for the survival of an individual and organisation.", "optc": "is the product of an individual's physical and mental energy.", "optd": "is the external force which induces an individual to contribute his efforts.", "opte": "makes organisation and society inseparable.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Due to enormous profits involved in smuggling, hundreds of persons have been attracted towards this anti-national activity. Some of them became millionaires overnight. India has a vast coastline both on the Eastern and Western Coast. It has been a heaven for smugglers who have been carrying on their activities with great impunity. There is no  doubt, that from time to time certain seizures were made by the enforcement authorities, during raids and ambush but even allowing these losses the smugglers made huge profits. The passage best supports the statement that", "opta": "smuggling hampers the economic development of a nation.", "optb": "smuggling ought to be curbed.", "optc": "authorities are taking strict measures to curb smuggling.", "optd": "smuggling is fast increasing in our country owing to the quick profit it entails.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Though the waste of time or the expenditure on fashions is very large, yet fashions have come to stay. They will not go, come what may. However, what is now required is that strong efforts should be made to displace the excessive craze for fashion from the minds of these youngsters. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "fashion is the need of the day.", "optb": "the excessive craze for fashion is detrimental to one's personality.", "optc": "the hoard for fashion should be done away with so as not to let down the constructive development.", "optd": "work and other activities should be valued more than the outward appearance.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "One of the important humanitarian by-products of technology is the greater dignity and value that it imparts to human labour. In a highly industrialized society, there is no essential difference between Brahmin and Dalit, Muslim and Hindu; they are equally useful and hence equally valuable for in the industrial society individual productivity fixes the size of the pay cheque and this fixes social status. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "technology decides individual's social status.", "optb": "castes and religions are man-made.", "optc": "human labour has dignity and value.", "optd": "all individuals, irrespective of caste and creed, are born equal.", "opte": "industrial society is a great leveller of men.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The future of women in India is quite bright and let us hope that they will justify their abilities by rising to the occasion. Napoleon was right when he declared that by educating the women we can educate the whole nation. Because a country can never rise without the contribution of 50% of their population. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "India is striving hard for the emancipation of women.", "optb": "all women should be well educated.", "optc": "a nation can progress only when women are given equal rights and opportunities as men.", "optd": "women ought to be imparted full freedom to prove their worth and contribute to the progress of the nation.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The prevention of accidents makes it necessary not only that safety devices be used to guard exposed machinery but also that mechanics be instructed in safety rules which they must follow for their own protection, and that lighting in the plant be adequate. The passage best supports the statement that industrial accidents -", "opta": "are always avoidable;", "optb": "may be due to ignorance.", "optc": "cannot be entirely overcome.", "optd": "can be eliminated with the help of safety rules.", "opte": "usually result from inadequate machinery.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To forgive an injury is often considered to be a sign of weakness; it is really a sign of strength. It is easy to allow oneself to be carried away by resentment and hate into an act of vengeance; but it takes a strong character to restrain those natural passions. The man who forgives an injury proves himself to be the superior of the man who wronged himself and puts the wrong-doer to shame. The passage best supports' the statement that:", "opta": "the sufferer alone knows the intensity of his sufferings.", "optb": "people tend to forgive the things happened in the past.", "optc": "natural passions are difficult to suppress.", "optd": "mercy is the noblest form of revenge.", "opte": "a person with calm and composed nature has depth of thought and vision.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Industrial exhibitions play a major role in a country's economy. Such exhibitions, now regularly held in Delhi, enable us to measure the extent of our own less advanced industrial progress and the mighty industrial power and progress of countries like the U.K., U.S.A. and Russia whose pavilions are the centres of the greatest attention and attractions. The passage best supports the statement that industrial exhibitions -", "opta": "greatly tax the poor economies.", "optb": "are more useful for the developed countries like U.S.A. whose products stand out superior to those of the developing countries.", "optc": "are not of much use to the countries who are industrially backward.", "optd": "boost up production qualitatively and quantitatively by analytical comparison of a country's products with those of the developed countries.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The school has always been the most important means of transferring the wealth of tradition form one generation to the next. This applies today in an even higher degree than in former times for, through the modern development of economy, the family as bearer of tradition and education has become weakened. This passage best supports the statement that for transferring the wealth of tradition from one generation to the next  -", "opta": "there are means other than the school.", "optb": "several different sources must be tried.", "optc": "economic development plays a crucial role", "optd": "modern technology must be put to use.", "opte": "family, as ever, is the most potent means.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Emerson said that the poet was landlord, Sealord, airlord. The flight of imagination made the poet master of land, sea and air. But a poet's dream of yesterday becomes today an actual achievement and a reality for all men. Even those who invented, improved and perfected the aeroplane could hardly have dreamt of the possibility of flight into outer space. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "seemingly impossible imaginations make one a good poet,", "optb": "all imaginations become a reality some day.", "optc": "what man imagined has never been impossible; he has always turned it a reality through his conception of ideas and sheer hard labour.", "optd": "man has reached the climax of technological development with his exploration into outer space.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is up to our government and planners to devise ways and means for the mobilisation of about ten crore workers whose families total up about forty crore men, women and children. Our agriculture is over-manned. A lesser number of agriculturists would mean more purchasing or spending power to every agriculturist. This will result in the shortage of man-power for many commodities to be produced for which there will be a new demand from a prosperous agrarian class. This shortage will be removed by surplus man-power released from agriculture as suggested above. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "employment in production is more fruitful than employment in agriculture.", "optb": "Indian economy is in a poor shape basically due to improper mobilisation of man-power.", "optc": "a shift of labour from agricultural sector to the industrial sector would uplift the living standard.", "optd": "the industrial sector is labour-deficient while the agricultural sector is over-manned in our country.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Exports and imports, a swelling favourable balance of trade, investments and bank-balances, are not an index or a balance sheet of national prosperity. Till the beginning of the Second World War, English exports were noticeably greater than what they are today. And yet England has greater national prosperity today than it ever had. Because the income of average Englishmen, working as field and factory labourers, clerks, policemen, petty shopkeepers and shop assistants, domestic workers and other low-paid workers, has gone up. The passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "a country's economic standard can be best adjudged by per capital income.", "optb": "a country's balance of trade is the main criteria of determining its economic prosperity.", "optc": "a nation's economy strengthens with the increase in exports.", "optd": "English trade has continually increased since the Second World War.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Satisfaction with co-workers, promotion opportunities, the nature of work, and pay goes with high performance among those with strong growth needs. Among those with weak growth needs, no such relationship is present - and, in fact, satisfaction with promotion opportunities goes with low performance. This passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "satisfaction is an inevitable organisational variable.", "optb": "job satisfaction and performance are directly and closely related.", "optc": "relationship between job satisfaction and performance is moderated by growth need.", "optd": "every organisation has few employees having weak growth need.", "opte": "high performance is essential for organisational effectiveness.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The only true education comes through the stimulation of the child's powers by the demands of the social situations in which he finds himself. Through these demands he is stimulated to act as a member of a unity, to emerge from his original narrowness of action and feeling, and to conceive himself from the standpoint of the welfare of the group to which he belongs. The passage best supports the statement that real education -", "opta": "will take place if the children imbibe action and feeling.", "optb": "will take place if the children are physically strong.", "optc": "is not provided in our schools today.", "optd": "comes through the interaction with social situations.", "opte": "comes from the self-centred approach of the students.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The press should not be afraid of upholding and supporting a just and righteous cause. It should not be afraid of criticising the government in a healthy manner. The press has to be eternally vigilant to protect the rights of the workers, backward and suppressed sections of the society. It should also give a balanced view of the things so that people can be helped in the formation of a healthy public opinion. The passage best supports the statement that", "opta": "press has a great role to play in a democracy.", "optb": "the press is the only means to project to the masses the policies of the government.", "optc": "the freedom of press is essential for the proper functioning of democracy.", "optd": "the press can be used by the governments as an effective media for the upliftment of the backward sections of society.", "opte": "all the information given by the press should be well-articulated so as to gain a good opinion towards the ruling party.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Throughout the ages the businessman has helped build civilisation's great cities, provided people with luxuries and artists with patronage, and lift his fellow citizens to understand the standard of living. In the last few centuries the businessman has seeded the Industrial Revolution around the world.  The passage best supports the statement that the businessman -", "opta": "is accountable to the society.", "optb": "lives luxurious and comfortable life.", "optc": "is the beneficiary of the Industrial Revolution.", "optd": "is capable of raising his standard of living.", "opte": "has contributed to the growth of civilisation.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "There is a shift in our economy from a manufacturing to a service orientation. The increase in service-sector will require the managers to work more with people rather than with objects and things from the assembly line. This passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "managers should have a balanced mind.", "optb": "assembly line will exist in service organisations.", "optc": "interpersonal skills will become more important in the future work place.", "optd": "manufacturing organisations ignore importance of people.", "opte": "service organisations will not deal with objects and things.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The virtue of art does not allow the work to be interfered with or immediately ruled by anything other than itself. It insists that it alone shall touch the work in order to bring it into being. Art requires that nothing shall attain the work except through art itself. This passage best supports the statement that:", "opta": "art is governed by external rules and conditions.", "optb": "art is for the sake of art and life.", "optc": "art is for the sake of art alone.", "optd": "artist realises his dreams through his artistic creation.", "opte": "artist should use his art for the sake of society.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}